Joseph Sheppard Barnett, Jr., papers, Inclusive: 1916-1951, undated, Bulk: 1943-1945
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Joseph Sheppard Barnett, Jr., papers
Inclusive: 1916-1951, undated, Bulk: 1943-1945
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
499
Barnett, Joseph Sheppard, Jr., 1892 - 1972
3 document boxes and 1 oversized box.
The Joseph Sheppard Barnett, Jr., papers contain letters, documents, and publications that relate to Barnett’s time in the armed forces during World War I and World War II, including many military documents from his time overseeing training at Camp Howze, Texas.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Joseph Sheppard Barnett, Jr., was born 1892 September 8 in Texas. In 1917, Barnett joined the army, training at Camp Travis, and eventually fought on the front lines in 1918, remaining in Germany with his regiment until at least March of 1919. After World War I, he remained in the army, reaching the rank of captain by 1931, when he served as the Assistant Plans and Training Officer and the Regimental Gas Officer for the 143rd Infantry at Camp Hulen near Palacios, Texas.
During World War II, as a lieutenant colonel, he commanded the 3rd Battalion of the 143rd Combat Team, receiving the Army Commendation Medal for gallantry in battle on 1943 September 13 in Italy. While commanding the 36th Infantry at Salerno, Italy, Barnett was wounded in the leg by a shell fragment. Barnett returned home to recover at McCloskey General Hospital in Temple, Texas. After his recovery, Barnett oversaw training, first at Camp Fannin, Texas and then at Camp Howze, Texas. He died on 1972 June 9.
Scope and Content
The Joseph Sheppard Barnett, Jr., papers consist of materials from 1916-1951, with some undated items. The papers reflect Barnett’s military career during World War I and World War II, recording his decision to join the armed forces in World War I and his oversight of training at Camp Howze, Texas after being wounded at Salerno during World War II.
Series I, Correspondence, includes outgoing correspondence (related to World War I) and incoming correspondence (related to World War II). Series II, Newspaper Clippings, contains clippings from local newspapers about World War II mentioning or interviewing Barnett. Series III, Military Documents, contains military records, memos, forms, and other materials connected to Barnett’s military career. The undated folder contains a cardboard practice sighting device. Series IV, Photographs, consists of photographs of Barnett. Series IV, Literary Productions, contains military publications, including regulation booklets, training materials, and pocket guides, as well as a 1931 camp annual from Camp Hulen, Texas, and posters depicting the campaigns of the 36th Infantry Division in World War II.
Arrangement
The collection received some initial processing and was divided into two boxes. The first box contained what appeared to be five series: “Correspondence”, “Newspaper Clippings,” “Company Rosters,” “Military Training and Procedure,” and “Photographs.” The second box contained several books, manuals, and pamphlets. The documents in the “Military Training and Procedure” folders appeared to be arranged in alphabetical order of topic based on the folder titles, but the documents in the folder presented no clear arrangement or order.
Currently, the collection includes five series: I. Correspondence, II. Newspaper Clippings, III. Military Documents, IV. Photographs, V. Literary Productions. Although some series titles were kept (“Correspondence,” “Newspaper Clippings,” and “Photographs”), others were reorganized. “Company Rosters,” “Military Training and Procedure,” and a few items from “Correspondence” were combined into a single series labelled “Military Documents” and rearranged chronologically except for instances when later documents were stapled to earlier documents. In those cases, the later documents remain attached to the earlier documents. The publications in the second box were combined into a series titled “Literary Productions.”
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 499. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. “Joseph Sheppard Barnett II.” Memorial #103395818. Databases. Accessed 2020 September 15.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
United States. Army -- Officers -- Correspondence.; United States. Army -- Officers -- Training of.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 36th -- History.
Subjects
Military training camps -- Texas -- Cooke County; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Instructional and educational works.; Military records.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1917-1951; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series includes outgoing correspondence (related to World War I) and incoming correspondence (related to World War II). The series is in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Postcards
  - Outgoing, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incoming, 1942-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1943-1945; 2
  General condition: Average.
  This series contains clippings from local newspapers about World War II mentioning or interviewing Barnett. The series is in average condition.
  - Newspaper Clippings, circa 1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1945 August 14-December 16 (Box [1029] OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1943-1945 (Box [1029] OVZ, Folder 2)
- Military Documents, 1916-1945; 3
  This series contains military records, memos, forms, and other materials connected to Barnett’s military career. The series is in average condition.
  - Military Documents, 1916-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Military Documents, 1944 March 6-October 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Military Documents, 1944 November 3-17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Military Documents, 1944 November 18-27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Military Documents, 1944 December 2-8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Military Documents, 1944 December 9-31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Military Documents, 1945 January 3-February 26 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Military Documents, 1945 February 21-22 (Box [1029] OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Military Documents, 1945 March 3-April 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Military Documents, 1945 May 1-November 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Military Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographs, 1943-1943; 4
  This series consists of photographs of Barnett. The series is in good condition.
  Photographic print
  - Photographs, 1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box [1029] OVZ, Folder 4)
- Literary Productions, 1916-1945; 5
  This series contains military publications, including regulation booklets, training materials, and pocket guides, as well as a 1931 camp annual from Camp Hulen, Texas, and posters depicting the campaigns of the 36th Infantry Division in World War II. The series is in average condition.
  - Drill Regulations and "The Soldier", 1916-1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Camp Annual: 143rd Infantry, 1931 August 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Military Booklets, 1941-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Technical Manual: Use of Foreign Maps, 1942 November 5 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Military Justice Procedure, 1945 February (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General, 1943-1945 (Box [1029] OVZ, Folder 5)
  - Training Materials (1 of 7), 1943 December 15-1945 February 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Training Materials (2 of 7), 1944 February 1-1945 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Training Materials (3 of 7), 1943 November 15-1944 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Training Materials (4 of 7), 1944 January 1-December 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Training Materials (5 of 7), 1944 January 1-1945 January 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Training Materials (6 of 7), 1943 December 1-1945 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Training Materials (7 of 7), 1943 August 15-1945 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subject Schedules (1 of 6), 1944 October 15-1945 January 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Subject Schedules (2 of 6), 1944 February 15-1945 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Subject Schedules (3 of 6), 1944 April 1-1945 January 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subject Schedules (4 of 6), 1944 November 1-1945 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Subject Schedules (5 of 6), 1944 February 1-1945 June 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subject Schedules (6 of 6), 1944 May 15-1945 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)